Register of the Nicolas, Prince of Romania Papers, 1907-1984
Hoover Institution Archives
Nicolas, Prince of Romania Papers,
1907-1984
82002
Nicolas, Prince of Romania, 1903-1978
8 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes (4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoirs, other writings, correspondence, genealogical charts, legal and financial papers, printed matter, and photographs, relating to the royal family of Romania, the history of the House of Hohenzollern, and Romanian émigré affairs
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Romania--Court and courtiers; Hohenzollern, House of; Romanians in foreign countries; Romania
Biographical Note
Prince Nicolas was the second son of King Ferdinand and of Queen Maria of Romania, brother of Marie, queen of Yugoslavia, and of Elizabeth, queen of Greece.
He was born on August 18, 1903 and studied in the English Navy School of Malta. After 1927, during the minority of his nephew, the future King Michael I, he served as Romanian Regent (together with the Patriarch Miron Cristea and the president of the Court of Cassation, Gh. Buzdugan).
In 1930 he was instrumental in bringing back his elder brother Carol, who had gone into voluntary exile in 1925, and helped to proclaim him king. However, he was exiled in 1937 for political opposition to the dictatorship of the new monarch. Except for his mother's funeral in 1938, he never went back to Romania.
During his exile, in Italy, Switzerland, and Spain, Prince Nicolas was politically active. He founded the Romanian Center for Research (Centre Roumain de Recherches) in France, patronized by the French Academy, as well as the Romanian Cultural Foundation: Princess Ioana (Fundatia Culturala Romana: Printesa Ioana) in Germany. He participated in numerous meetings of Romanian émigrés from all over Europe, gave speeches at Romanian cultural events, and addressed radio broadcasts to Romanians from Romania and abroad. He also started two Romanian publications in Madrid.
He married Joana Doletti in 1963 and, following her death, Thereza Figueira de Mello. Prince Nicolas died in 1978.
Scope and Content
This collection consists mainly of Prince Nicolas's memoirs and his writings on political, social, religious, educational, and economic conditions in Romania. Also of special interest are the materials related to the Romanian émigré associations and to the Hohenzollern dynasty, found in the subject file.
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1949-1979. (Box No. 1)
  Includes biographical notes, inventories of personal objects, and miscellaneous papers related to Prince Nicolas's citizenship, marriages, succession, and death, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1943-1977. (Box No. 2)
  Correspondence arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1948-1970. (Box No. 3-5)
  Includes Prince Nicolas's memoirs, speeches, interviews, and miscellaneous writings arranged chronologically by title
- Subject File, 1923-1984. (Box No. 6-7)
  Includes miscellaneous material arranged alphabetically by subject, and related mainly to Romanian émigré associations, to conditions in Romania, and to Romanians politics
- Photographs, 1907-1977. (Box No. 8-10)
  319 prints depicting mainly Prince Nicolas and members of the Hohenzollern dynasty
- Oversize File, 1912-1929. (Box No. 10)
  Genealogical charts, maps, printed matter relating to Romania and the Hohenzollern dynasty, and reproductions of pencil drawings depicting Prince Nicolas and Princess Ioana of Hohenzollern, arranged alphabetically by physical form
Container List
- Biographical File, 1949- 1979
  - Biographical notes, portraits, etc. on Prince Nicolas, by others, 1949-1979 (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - Clippings relating to Prince Nicolas's various activities, 1950-1971 (Folder 2)
  - Inventories of personal objects, 1963-1973. Includes letters and telegrams related to their acquisition, value, and sale (Folder 3-4)
  - List of Prince Nicolas's books (Folder 5)
  - Subject File
    - Citizenship. Official papers
      - Romanian, 1964-1969 (Folder 6)
      - Swiss, 1974 (Folder 7)
      - Spanish, 1977-1978 (Folder 8)
    - Death. Includes notes relating to his death, memorial service, obituaries, 1978 (Folder 9)
    - Marriage, 1967-1975. Documents relating to Prince Nicolas's marriage to Thereza Figueira de Mello. Includes mariage certificate and statement relating to the Prince's renunciation of the Orthodox faith and adoption of the catholic one (Folder 10)
    - Reception given by Prince Nicolas in honor of the Romanian colony in Spain, 1953 December 19. Letters and telegrams (Folder 11)
    - Succession, 1969-1979. Includes Prince Nicolas's concession of Spanish passport, and his will (Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1943- 1977
  - General, 1943-1977 (Box 2.)
    - A (Folder 1)
    - B (Folder 2)
    - C (Folder 3)
    - D-E (Folder 4)
    - F-G (Folder 5)
    - H-J (Folder 6)
    - L (Folder 7)
    - M (Folder 8)
    - N-O (Folder 9)
    - Q-R (Folder 10)
    - S (Folder 11)
    - T (Folder 12)
    - U-W (Folder 13)
  - Unidentified, 1946-1978 (Folder 14)
  - Biserica Romana Ortodoxa din Germania, 1975 (Folder 15)
  - Centre Roumain de Recherches, 1949-1976 (Folder 16)
  - Cowles, J. H. (Sovereign Commander, Ancient and Accepted Scottish Rite of Freemasonry, Southern Jurisdiction, USA), 1949 (Folder 17)
  - Hohenzollern, Fritz de, 1947-1970 (Folder 18)
  - Gafencu, Grigore, n.d. (Folder 19)
  - George II, King of Greece, 1945 (Folder 20)
  - George VI, King of Great Britain, 1945 (Folder 21)
  - Goma, Paul, 1977 (Folder 22)
  - Maniu, Iuliu, 1944 (Folder 23)
  - Mary, Consort of George V, King of Great Britain, 1945 (Folder 24)
  - Michael I, King of Romania, 1945-1951 (Folder 25)
  - Pius XII, Pope, 1949 (Folder 26)
  - Radescu, Ionel, 1977 (Folder 27)
  - Ratiu, Ion, 1977 (Folder 28)
  - Tautu, Aloisie, 1942-1957 (Folder 29)
  - Xeni, X., 1943-1945 (Folder 30)
- Speeches and Writings, 1948-1970
  - "Crestinismul Roman sub ocupatie bolsevica," n.d. Typescript (Box 3., Folder 1)
  - "Cuvintul Altetei Sale Regale Princepelui Nicolae," n.d. Typescript (Folder 2)
  - "Cuvintul A.S.R. Principelui Nicolae al Romaniei cu ocazia zilei de 10 Mai, ziua regilor Romaniei si a Independentei," n.d. Typescript (Folder 3)
  - "Declaracion" (concerning the title of 'Alteza Real'), n.d. Typescript (Folder 4)
  - Interview, Libertatea, n.d. Typescript (Folder 5)
  - Interview, Patria, n.d. Typescript (Folder 6)
  - Interview given on the occasion of Antonescu's overthrow (1944 August 23), n.d. Notes and typescript (Folder 7)
  - Interview given to Horia Stamatu, n.d. Notes and typescript (Folder 8)
  - Memoirs, n.d. Holograph. Includes English version (Folder 9-12)
  - "Partea Politica: De la Saint-Aulaire citire," n.d. Typescript (partial) (Folder 13)
  - Radio broadcast transcript, given on Christmas, n.d. Typescript (Folder 14)
  - Speech given on the occasion of the Romanian Week in Freiburg, Germany, n.d. Notes (Folder 15)
  - Untitled writings on political, social, religious, educational, and economic conditions in Romania, n.d. Holographs. Includes some Spanish translations (Box 4., Folder 1-7)
  - "Dare de seama asupra deplasarii in Germania a delegatiei Caroman dela 30 iunie," 1948. Typescript (Box 5., Folder 1)
  - "Aide-memoire asupra situatiei si stadiului diferitelor chestiuni, asa dupa cum au evoluat in ultimul timp si in special in ultimele 10 zile, si in masura in care se pot descrie," 1949. Typescript (Folder 2)
  - Interview, Sigmarigen, Germany, 1949. Typescript (Folder 3)
  - "Con el Principe Prince Nicolas de Romania," interview, Madrid, Madrid, 1950. Printed copy (Folder 4)
  - "Madrid es una ciudad encantadora," interview, Arriba, 1950. Printed copy (Folder 5)
  - "Radiobotschaft von Seiner Koeniglichen Hoheit, Prinz Nikolaus von Rumanien," Madrid, 1950. Typescript (Folder 6)
  - "Sistematica destruccion de Romania bajo el dominio ruso," interview, A.B.C., Madrid, 1950. Printed copy (Folder 7)
  - "Soy un soldado de primera linea," interview, YA, Madrid, 1950. Printed copy (Folder 8)
  - "Message de S.A.R. le Prince Nicolas de Roumanie transmis par radio le 25 decembre 1950," Madrid, 1950 December 25. Typescript. Includes Romanian and German versions (Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 1950-1970 (Folder 10-11)
  - "Aide-memoire" (on the occasion of Prince Nicolas's first visit to Franco, in 1950), 1951. Typescript (Folder 12)
  - Conference paper, Paris, 1952. Typescript (Folder 13)
  - Speech, dinner given in Prince Nicolas's honor by the Anglo-American Association of Paris, Paris, 1952. Typescript (Folder 14)
  - "Romania 1952: Situatie, istorie, rost, structura si problema," Paris, 1952. Typescript. Includes French version (Folder 15)
  - Speech given on the occasion of the 10th of May, Madrid, 1952. Typescript (Folder 16)
  - Radio broadcast transcript given at Easter, Madrid, 1953. Typescript (Folder 17)
  - "De vorba cu A.S. Regala principele Nicolae al Romaniei," Madrid, 1954. Typescript (Folder 18)
  - "Mesaj al Principelui Nicolae catre lumea libera," Madrid, 1954. Typescript (Folder 19)
- Subject File, 1923- 1984
  - A.C.A.R.D.A. (Cultural Association of the Romanians from the UK), 1964-1978. Clippings, letters, memoranda, magazines, biographical notes on Ion Ratiu, miscellaneous materials (Box 6., Folder 1)
  - Anglo-Rumanian Timber Co., 1946. Memorandum (Folder 2)
  - Antonescu, Ion, 1969 (Folder 3)
  - Argetoianu, Constantin, 1969. Clippings (Folder 4)
  - Association Cultural Romana en Espana, 1957. Note on the 80th celebration of Romanian independence (Folder 5)
  - Association des Chevaliers Italiens de l'Ordre Souverain Militaire de Malte," 1924. Statute. Includes Italian version (Folder 6)
  - Brosteni domain, n.d. Notes (Folder 7)
  - Boldeanu, Vasile, 1972-1974. Letters (Folder 8)
  - Canini, Marco Antonio, 1938. Writing by Nicolae Iorga (Folder 9)
  - Carol I Foundation, 1951 (Folder 10)
  - Carol II, King of Romania, 1944 (Folder 11)
  - Centre Intellectuel Roumain de Recherches, 1949-1951. Notes, founding papers, letters, reports, memoirs (Folder 12)
  - Cold War, 1948-1951. Clippings (Folder 13)
  - Comission Nationale Roumaine pour l'Union Latine, n.d. (Folder 14)
  - Comitetul Roman din Germania, 1949-1955. Notes, letters (Folder 15)
  - Davila, Carol, n.d. Clipping (Folder 16)
  - Dianu, N., 1947-1955. Includes his writings on Alexandru Cretzianu and on the association "Pro- Bassarabia" (Folder 17)
  - Doletti, Joana, 1937-1952. Letter from the Bishop of Lausanne, Geneva and Fribourg, letter about her by the Romanian Consul in Italy, and official papers (Folder 18)
  - Elisabeth, Consort of George II, King of Greece. Clipping, 1956 (Folder 19)
  - Europe, Eastern, 1956. Bulletin Europa Oprimada (Folder 20)
  - Fundatia Culturala "Printesa Ioana," 1966. Notes concerning its purpose and means (Folder 21)
  - Hohenzollern, House of, n.d. Notes, clippings, genealogies (Folder 22-24)
  - Ileana, Princess of Romania, 1984. Letter addressed to Simon and Schuster, Inc. (Folder 25)
  - Jews, 1953. Letter to the editor entitled "The Russian Purge: A Jewish Point of View" by Moische Benache (Box 7., Folder 1)
  - Lupescu, Magda, n.d. Biographical note (Folder 2)
  - Marcel, Gabriel, n.d. Clipping (Folder 3)
  - Matasescu, Ion, 1949. Letter (Folder 4)
  - Michael I, King of Romania, 1969-1990. Clippings (Folder 5)
  - Monaco, n.d. Brochure in regard to refugees (Folder 6)
  - Ordre Militaire et Hospitalier de Saint-Lazare de Jerusalem, 1974. Bulletin (Folder 7)
  - Peter the Great, n.d. Typescript of his political testament. Consists of English, German and Romanian versions (Folder 8)
  - Romania
    - General. Note concerning some Romanian cultural materials from the Swiss Legation in Madrid, n.d. (Folder 9)
    - Drama. Includes a play by I. L. Caragiale, entitled "Fatalidad" (Folder 10)
    - Constitution
      - 1923 (Folder 11-12)
      - 1948 (Folder 13)
    - Foreign relations
      - General-1944-1989. Clippings (Folder 14)
      - Spain, 1971. Clipping (Folder 15)
    - History-1914-1944. Includes writings of D. Damaceanu, G. Gafencu, Petrin(?), A. Simion (Folder 16)
  - Romanian Legionaire Movement, 1968. Newsletter issue (Tara si exilul) (Folder 17)
  - Romanian Orthodox Church, 1979 (Folder 18)
  - Romanians in foreign countries, 1971-1977. Notes, clippings, letters, and memoranda (Folder 19)
  - Thereza, Princess of Hohenzollern, 1978-1979. Biographical note and letters from Ion Ratiu, Horia Stamate, and others (Folder 20)
  - Miscellany (Folder 21-22)
- Photographs, 1907- 1977
  - 35 prints depicting Prince Nicolas, 1907-1977 (Box 8., Folder 1)
  - 132 prints depicting Prince Nicolas and others, including Princess Ioana of Hohenzollern; Princess Thereza of Hohenzollern; Elizabeth, Consort of George II, King of Greece; Ferdinand, King of Romania; Marie, Consort of Ferdinand, King of Romania; Victoria-Eugenia, Consort of Alfonso XIII, King of Spain; Simeon II, King of Bulgaria; Leonida Georgievna, Grand Duchess of Russia; and Vladimir Kirillovich, Grand Duke of Russia, 1930-1970 (Folder 2-3)
  - 7 prints depicting Princess Ioana, 1950-1957 (Folder 4)
  - 3 prints depicting Princess Thereza, 1969 (Folder 5)
  - 1 print depicting Elizabeth, Consort of George II, King of Greece, n.d. (Folder 6)
  - 6 prints depicting aspects of Romanian civilization, 1930-1958 (Folder 7)
  - 3 prints depicting members of the House of Hohenzollern, 1922-1934 (Folder 8)
  - 8 unidentified prints, n.d. (Folder 9)
  - 2 albums containing 114 prints depicting art objects, n.d. (Box 9., Folder 1-2)
  - 10 prints depicting Prince Nicolas; Princess Ioana of Hohenzollern; Elizabeth, Consort of George II, King of Greece, and others, n.d. (Box 10., Folder 1)
- Oversize File, 1912- 1929
  - Genealogical charts related to the House of Hohenzollern, n.d. (Box 10., Folder 2)
  - Issues of L'Illustration, 1926-1929, and La Ilustracion, 1912. Includes articles on Romania (Folder 3)
  - Maps of the Brosteni domain, n.d. (Folder 4)
  - Reproductions of pencil drawings depicting Prince Nicolas and Princess Ioana of Hohenzollern, n.d. (Folder 5)